right great we've already had a great
conversation
but now we're finally recording so um
really
lovely to speak with you again alex
and thanks for making time um i've
actually
spent the last hour looking on the
internet a coup
a couple of old talks of years and there
was one
from i think it was 2013 that had x talk
um where when i watched it
i i thought you it was literally like
you were speaking
out of my book designing regenerative
cultures so i
for me this is is almost like a um
a proof that when you when you try to
serve
this regenerative impulse you actually
we're speaking out of gaia we're
speaking out of the earth
and like so many of the ideas that you
were like i hadn't seen this talk when i
was writing my book i
saw it today for the first time but so
much is alignment
in terms of your vision for over the
last
and 25 years with why you even started
guayaqui with this impulse of
um we need to give back more than we
take we need to
regenerate we need to go beyond just
not having a negative impact or a
minimal impact but
actually try to have a maximum impact
but on the positive side and regenerate
things so
i i would love for you to tell a little
bit of the story how you
um like what
what made you decide to study food
science and
and um move to california and and how
did
your childhood in argentina was it in
argentina and
um paraguay or yes it was
yes it was in both i mean back and forth
but um
i always tell the story that you know
that
we all are you know the consequence of
of an act of love
so you know so i was conceived in
paraguay
that's what i you know my parents have
shared that and you know there's
definitely then
you know a strong spirit in me
of the warani culture that it's so alive
in paraguay and i love
paralyzed just i feel like um there's a
strong identity there's a strong part of
me
that is comes from there whatever it's
you know a square knee spirit that it's
you know in my body now or who knows
but uh i just also you know
being brought up in argentina in in a
scottish
school you know that's 182 years old you
know it's called saint andrews and
it's part of the saint andrews you know
school in scotland so
that was brought up very british very
scottish and
bilingual um with all the traditions and
you know that that you know comes with
um
but i i sort of like always been in
contact with nature because my
you know my dad is is an agronomist
so um we would just spend a lot of time
you know weekends
practically every weekend of my life as
a child
you know just visiting farms and and um
my dad was an advisor for many many many
farms and
um besides having his own uh
family farm but um you know one of
probably you know probably it's in in in
me that
that smell you know that i can recognize
of the year of mate
you know being savado by by my mom
while my dad was like you know driving
in the car
and my mom would pass the gourd you know
to my dad and my dad would
drink the mud and keep driving and and
there was
probably conversations that they were
having
that i didn't understand as a child you
know the the complexity of it
but somewhere i think it stayed you know
in me
as well because funny enough i mean as
an agronomist my dad always
has debated about you know the extension
of the agricultural
frontier on on forest areas in paraguay
and in argentina
and um you know and the consequences
that that
creates not only in the environment but
also
for the communities living in those in
those remnants of forests
you know so um you know i think
now i can i can just identify the whole
you know thread of oh i wonder how i
ended up
studying food science and looking for
you know
other horizons in california and moving
out of argentina
and um and just really going to
california
with with just probably the vision of of
finding diversity
and um how many people you know today
refer as
diversity as being the currency not only
for
survival of our species but i think
for for thriving you know you know
in in in our planet and i believe in
that you know and i think i'm just a
channel
i wasn't necessarily looking for
something specific for that career
um i wasn't like searching for for
destiny but really just
being open for destiny to come to me you
know i always sort of like
been driven by passion
and by my gut feelings and not
so much you know using my
rational level that that sort of like
came
always afterwards i said okay i feel
this
i feel like this is the way to go okay
let's figure it out kind of like the
vision and mission
how that is defined the vision being the
the why we do things and then
the the mission like okay now now let's
figure out how we're gonna do it
kind of thing right this was one of the
things you said in that talk which is
quite a long time ago
where you basically said that
fundamental
and like you have to start with the why
why you do things and and but i also
love the way
you tell the story of of you walking
into your classes with your
um thermos cannon and you're good and
and people being completely
like culturally not used to that and and
thinking you were
bringing in something to smoke pot in in
class and
um but also how it it allowed you to
start conversations because people were
kept asking and and i think that's the
beauty of of
is that it is a really social ritual um
an invitation to sit together and
converse and
like i would call it live the questions
together
um spend like build community build
trust build understanding around
um a ritual that is ancient
yeah it is it is ancient it comes from
the guaranise you know and
they they really you know would start
the day
you know with this ritual of of you know
preparing first a sacred fire so the
fire
it's really speaking to to the community
that's why they call it the sacred fire
they usually you know would put the wood
in a in with with facing north south
east and west and then heating the water
in the fire
and then the water being the female
aspect and the board being the male
aspect and combining those two and um
and allowing each person to drink one
gourd in the morning
and share their dreams what were their
dreams last night
so then the shaman or the head of the
the tribe the only thing that
he would do he would just interpret the
collective dreams
you know what is the message in that
collective dream and then
he would be the one deciding okay this
is what we should do today
or go on farm and to the chakras
you know what they call the chakras is
funny enough
chakra they call it it's it's a small
piece of
plot of of land you know that they slash
and burn and
and they you know they with the biochar
actually you know
cultivated that area and these these
farm areas
chakras is it's a sacred place for for
the guarani culture
it's a place where they actually would
go and you know
um make love you know that's
in in the chakras right so so then for
them
it you know this decisions um on a daily
basis will
will be made um by by this
daily mantras of sharing the gourd and
sharing the dreams you know so
it's very community oriented and um and
then at the end of the day they would do
the same thing
and just say hey how was the day how you
know
what did we learn imagine what a ritual
like that would do to a community
imagine how how much
trust mutual understanding how how much
conflict avoidance like because
you didn't directly hear where most
people are coming from in that day
and and so it's it's a bit like i
remember at um
living at finton every kind of work
group
was always started with an attunement
which was a sort of very short
check-in but which for a lot of people
initially feels like well we've got a
lot of work to do whether you spend half
an hour attuning to
before we get going but by doing that it
makes the
the flow afterwards so much more
powerful because you you don't
um run into frictions because you know
if somebody had a bad dream or a bad
morning and and and you much more
attuned to the common goal and
it's fascinating yeah yes over the world
they've been rituals like that but we
we all now live in kind of nuclear
family
or too many of us live in nuclear family
situations where that's completely lost
yeah and you know one more thing that
it's you know that we started a
conversation talking about time
and um you know it's interesting
because time is is it's sort of like
you can bend time we can bend time
we time is something that it's it's a
lineal
um some mindset that we have you know
sort of
inherited but for the guaranise
time can be bended and how did they bend
time
well for them there was no concept of
ownership you know it was stewardship
yes so it was it was brought by
by the first conquistadores coming you
know to
to the americas that you know this land
is mine and you know and this is
that they were surprised
with this mindset of of ownership
that they they did not practice they
in fact um did not believe that they
owned
their own life right but
that they were not in control of their
life
and especially of of material
you know um ownerships of of they would
burn
everything that they would accumulate
and then
that was the time to to move on and
migrate
and that you during those migrations
obviously the
the weak or the elders or the sick would
die
and in fact the legend of the yeromati
is about you know
a young girl you know in an act of love
staying with an elder during these
migrations
and um and and and deciding to stay with
him
and and in as a gift the
the the spirit of the yarrow mata clan
became human in her
and passed on all the knowledge of the
planet
you know this knowledge of of not only
the health benefits
but of you know of sharing
of you know listening and and helping
the elders and the weak and the sick and
that they're also part of the community
so interesting enough
as they didn't have any belongings
um they were free of time
they believed that time was only only
being able to be
captured once you would you know
stick to a place and and come with that
mindset of ownership
then you were subject to time if you did
not
embrace you know belongings
then it's you could hop in time
with your spirit and you know generation
to generations
or in rivers or mountains or in forests
interesting well really i mean
fascinating
because i've always for the last 20
years i've
always felt that at the core of
this illusion that is also driving us
into believing that we're separate
um is somewhat a misperception of time
or it's the other way around that this
perception of separateness from um
the flow that actually brings us forth
make
makes us feel like
there is time um it's it's like like
what einstein called the illusion of
consciousness
of of the separate self um
i i sense that so many like even when
you were saying that you
you see yourself more like a channel
that's a much more flowing image of
something flowing through you and
manifesting as whatever you do that day
um it's very different from thinking of
oneself
as a being that has to do things in the
world
and um and i think so much of the
the real shift to coming home to place
and and relationship with plays in each
other is about that
that shift of um
yeah being more aware that
it's funny because you're saying they
they didn't think that they could
control their lives the very fact that
we
think we have much control about
anything
is is is actually a huge illusion um
and letting go of that makes you so much
more
creative in how you respond to what's in
front of you rather than what
what you think there should be because
of the story you've
you've been absorbing or told yourself
for far too long
but but i'd like to come
with david that you got together while
still in california and said
why don't we
create a mechanism that helps people and
planet
and do it through running a company
together
yeah we you know we met in college and
and um and and david was you know
starting a computer business i was
starting with
uh the yellow amateur business and then
he said i don't want to
sell computers this is so much more
interesting because it i think he felt
the spirit of the plan you know and he
started drinking you know mate
and of course as an american he was
he was brought up in a culture that did
not drink piero mate
as we do in argentina you know since
we're almost like
toddlers we're already you know sipping
the
the bomb and the gore so david um
david was the first one to really
you know um see it you know and he
understood that
that this was an enterprise
you know a for-profit project
you know that would would have uh
simply the premises switch so where the
goal was to
well we called it at that time you know
market-driven conservation
right so it was about conservation then
we we changed it to restoration and then
now we're talking about regeneration but
at that time in 1986 when we started
together um we we really
were coming from from the same paradigm
you know but different cultures and that
diversity
really was very powerful um i think that
by by david really understanding his
culture his american
you know culture and um amy bringing
this element of
of the year amateur culture from
argentina and how we share it and how
we create community with our families
and friends you know and
argentines and south americans are very
like
friendship and family is first right
it's it's that element of of
community and fun enough you know i
wonder where it comes from and we still
drink
tons of mother you know but
i for me the mate was just an extension
of my body
and you know it wasn't until another
culture started
questioning and and wanting to know more
about
yerba mate that i you know i paid
attention to
to to what was this that i was taking
for granted
in a way right and um and it
it allowed me to also strengthen my
identity and um and and this is what we
continue doing
about you know strengthening the
identities of
every relationship that we built it
doesn't matter you know
if you are paralyzed brazilian
indigenous non-american a student
you know in the markets as well
um we we you know we we put
as the focus the most important focus is
in the relationship that we build
you know between um human beings and
that
gets extended to all the living beings
right to to flora
and fauna and the air and the
and the rain water and so
from there we can build these these you
know
communities that thrive in life and
that's what we call they have come to
life
and we focus on these bright spots where
you know
life wants to come back you know and so
we look for
those areas where there's maybe higher
resilience
and you know close to national parks or
you know
areas also in communities in the united
states in markets where
people don't want to belong anymore to
to a system that doesn't make any more
sense
and that you know the the signs are
everywhere
and you know there's fires in california
going there is
social injustice there's well you know
these are the consequences
like you referred to many times you know
let's not focus on climate change let's
not focus
on you know the loss of diversity
because these are
or or you know fossil fuels the other or
the cow
these are real real consequences
you know like alan savory many times
says don't blame them
it's us it's our you know it's our
holistic management
it's our perception of life that needs
to be changed our mindsets that need to
be changed
this is fascinating music a while ago i
had this conversation with one of the
the great gurus of the sustainability
consultancy world
um john elkington who set up the
environmental data service in the late
80s and then set up
sustainability um and was the inventor
of the triple bottom line and then
um he later
created volans which which he now works
with um
and and he's recently written a book
called
green swans and this this idea of a
green swan
um is really quite a powerful one of
like picking up on the black swan
idea of events that that happen and then
continuously
make things go worse like a sort of
exponential
um path towards collapse in oblivion
and the idea of this greens one is
creating interventions that are actually
um increasing like that are salutogenic
that are increasing health that are
increasing abundance today
that are getting better and better um
and
it feels like so much what the the
outset of how
guayaquil has worked in in argentina
paraguay
and brazil with local communities
like in in one of the videos which is i
think seven years ago you you speak
about
a vision 2020 and it's kind of
interesting because we're talking in
um it was back then you said we want to
reforest 200 000 acres of rainforest
um through shade ground here
but in combination with working with
indigenous communities and actually
enable them to protect their forest and
have a livelihood
so that the second the social side of
that regenerative mission
was um giving a livelihood through that
work
to a thousand families how close
did you get to that mission
well you know we surpassed that mission
already um you know we're over
2 000 families um we were working with
over 200
000 acres and at that time you know
we were just you know using some
indicators and you know having
dashboards and
you know measuring on the impact which
is is it it is important
to do right and um
but um now things have also changed
because um now there is
you you can't do it anymore by yourself
you know and and
when we started with this mission we
were like okay we're gonna do this
working with
you know our farm suppliers and
indigenous communities
but during these 10 years what has
changed is that now we have a lot more
many more partners we have national
parks
we have biosphere reserves
you know declared by the united nations
or you know from
in in in parallel the baraka zhu reserve
for example
so you know ngos you know the
wida foundation which is you know an
extension of bird life
in in paraguay with the santa fe
national park
you know they are also partnering with
us
in in these last five years because
they they also figured out that the
model of conservation is just like
putting a fence
around you know national park or or
private biosphere
you know united nations reserve
was was not enough you know you have to
work
with all the social actors with all the
stakeholders living
in the buffer zones of these protected
areas
because otherwise you know it's
impossible to protect
um and the same thing happens in africa
it's it's highly expensive to put these
high huge electric fences to to to
you know to protect the elephants and
the lions which are you know
the most um dangerous species that if
they go outside these electric fences
they will destroy crops and
communities right so they have these
problems that
well we can't have these enormous
extensions with electro fences just
ridiculous you know
it doesn't make any sense but they
figured it out like
pinda in south africa figured out that
they needed to work with the communities
too
and and start working with with the zulu
communities
and they became you know the
stewardships of those
of these private reserves of these
national parks and that's
the same thing we started doing so
that's why we're
we have now you know expanded this
this mission of 200 000 acres and
and 1 000 families and we have surpassed
that and now we
even working with the amazon ecosystem
and and also paying for the service
that the amazon ecosystem is generating
through the sky rivers
and you know we get to that story like i
want to ask you about that because we
had a little bit of
um collaboration in the conversations
with martin ildebrandt
around that project but briefly back to
this working with the communities
um the are you aware that there's a big
project around
the masamara game reserve in kenya that
that
is basically it's a model which is
called land conservancies
where um you you work with the local
people
and actually pay them to help conserve
the land through more regenerative
farming um
have you looked into that model yes
yeah and and i think you know that is
that is stewardship that's the concept
of stewardship
really and uh by bringing in
the local communities and bringing in
also
you know the the government institutions
the
private initiatives in that that are for
profit as well
you know there's
there's there's so it's so much easier
to work in collaboration you know and
and not trying to be a don quixote
and fight you know against the windmills
and and you do everything right kind of
thing right
it's it that's an old paradigm
we we cannot continue you know striving
for our egos and to
you know i'm the successful
multi-million just jeff bezos you know
you know what does that mean really i
mean
what's behind them you know hundreds of
people
working for them to become the you know
the successful millionaires you know but
it's not really
them it's it's not only them it's them
but it's
also you know resources communities
employees you know um
public services they're allowing that to
happen you know consumers
right all of us who buy through amazon
you know
are part of that successful story as
well so i think that
you know the paradigm of just one
individual
one organization you know having a
mission
it's it's it's old already you know and
that's what it allowed
it has allowed i believe quietly as a
business
to be successful in these last 24 hours
we're gonna be 25 years next year you
set out i love that line
and then you ended that ted talk so long
ago with um
um
[Music]
um so it's it's not about creating the
best company in
in the world but it's about creating the
best company for the world and
and you you can only do that if you do
that with other companies together and
even like now seeing in the in the post
like the kind of pandemic world
how you're saying earlier before we
started recording
that everything was going fine because
you have strong teams in every place
and and you are decentralized like you
you you kind of
more more in control of your whole
supply chain because you've actually
built collaborations
along the entire supply chain which
which are
much more resilient than if it's just a
um
like you have team there so it's not not
an entire economic transaction it's it's
part of the
the the family that that makes guayaquil
happen um
it's a shared mission it becomes a
shared mission so
you know that's why we have i think
higher resilience in in these types of
crisis
um and and then at the same time it's
not that we control
anything it's we in guayaquil
i would say that we work it's it's kind
of a pathway
that we are you know in
going towards uncertainty really and we
in uncertainty is not something that we
are afraid of
yeah sorry but something that we find
that it's in those areas where things
are not controlled
that the answers you know to the
questions that we
we all you know developing
as as society
we can find them there you know
precisely yeah this is strongly related
to
like i find that one of the most
fascinating
aspects of your new collaboration with
guyana sonas and and the sky rivers were
what you that
you were mentioning earlier to is is
that you're not
like the conventional pathway right now
for companies who want to
show that they um want to have a
positive impact
is to in a sort of linear way
have it all measured and demonstrate
their
positive impact what what you're doing
with supporting an organization that is
helping
how many 30 indigenous tribes in an area
of
500 000 hectares of colombian rainforest
um to steward to continue to be the
stewards of their ancestral lands
and help them to
have sovereign sovereignty and and and
in their relationship with the national
government
to support them so they can basically
manage their own lands in the way that
they see fit
that's so much more of an indirect way
that you will never be able to get
all the detailed figures of where every
dollar that you spend on supporting this
process has
actually gone but but by by supporting
these people to protect that land you're
protecting
the forest that creates the rain that
waters
the bosque atlantico and basically
um waters the habamata plantations of
the the tribes that you work with in
in the atlantic but it it's
really demonstrating a level of systemic
thinking of understanding the gaian
patterns the the sky rivers
um that i haven't seen in in many
companies
um when did you start with that vision
of
working in that way i think from from
the start
really i mean from from from the initial
dna of of guayaqui you know was like
you know driven by by by
the gut feeling drew by you know well
i'm the guy
you know like that's a big
that's a big part of our body that you
know keeps our immune system too you
know
but that's another subject but but i
think that
if if we listen to our um
internal call you know or internal voice
that we all have in common these this
little voice that
speaks to us and and then you know
which that's the why that's the that's
our vision
right of of okay this is why i'm gonna
put things into action then it's the
mission that's how i'm gonna
do it right how am i gonna you know
accomplish or manifest my dream right
and then you have a set of values that
you say well
you know i'm not gonna do a certain
things because you have values right
and um i think that you know for
it it was embedded in in in the genesis
of waiakea you know and and i believe
that
it's due to the spirit of the plant you
know
what the plan comes to to in a way
you know humanize
and and put into action if we're open to
it
so it's not really like looking for
destiny but align being open to destiny
to come to you
you know it's sort of like switching the
mindsets
all the time and um it's interesting
enough then
guayaquil why did we choose that name
that's so hard to pronounce and what
does it
mean why a key you know it's the name of
our indigenous tribe in paraguay
now hunters and nomads that lived in the
forest
until the 1970s and um
and at the same time it's difficult to
pronounce so
with david we we sort of like why a key
imagine a door and why do you need a key
so and in a way and in a way this is
what we do you know it's
it's it sounds very hippy and sounds
very you know maybe very artistic
but it's it's we i think waiakee
is an opportunity for for everyone
that's part of kaiaki
to open doors of perception right
to just discover that there's so many
doors that we can open and they're all
there and we're free
to open them or not but the only reason
why we don't
is because there's uncertainty what's
behind the door
we're afraid many times to open them
but once you open them it's just
wonderful
like love it comes with pain and it
comes with suffering and it comes with
everything
you know it's not like it's only all
happiness and joy all the time
you know it's the ying and youngs and we
have to allow ourselves
to enter into that universal
perception of life that there is always
this yin and yangs
and um and not be afraid so guyaki
is discovering all the time new
doors of perception and the one of the
water was
recently in on the sky rivers and it
just
it was actually in 2018 that
i was in costa rica and you know and i
saw my
daughter and this other kid
playing in the water and i go oh my god
with all the metrics that we have as a b
corp you know and
with objectives and purpose and
everything that
then get sort of with our aspirations
and dreams
measured by all these indicators and we
have our
annual impact reports that we you know
are measuring
all the aluminum and packaging and you
know emissions and
trying to reduce them and trying to
regenerate
more life um we all of a sudden we
realized
that we were not measuring the water
so i was like oh my god you know but
it's
it's all the time you know it's okay you
know there's more going to come
there's there's more things that you
know that we
don't know that we're doing that we
might be doing wrong
or we're not measuring yet that we will
we will measure and this is an
opportunity
as a as a business to do it and um
and i think that with the sky rivers in
the amazon
we realized that you know the
the atlantic forest of cilibar
missionaries that we work in where
the yerramata is native to and it grows
in the shade
very well because it's in a species of
tree species
that grows as you see in in these back
images here
it grows in the forest well
that ecosystem depends on another
ecosystem
what do you mean it depends on yeah it
depends on another consistent depends
on the amazon forest because of the
rain water that the amazon produces 1
000 liters per tree
according to calorie and the scientists
measuring this for the last
50 years it's 1 000
liters that each tree produces
per day and there's probably 2 000
trees per hectare more or less
right so imagine the amount of water
that these trees
through the root system that's just
sucking all this water
and through the trans evaporation during
the day
when it's there's photosynthesis okay
it's just
creating all this water vapor that then
gets you know condensated as it reaches
a certain altitude creates a vacuum that
allows for the winds from the atlantic
to
you know come in you know
the elisos winds actually a generated
from
the sahara desert and all these
particles of phosphorus and
everything feeds into the amazon as well
but
this system this biotic
what they call the biotic pump right
and that you can see clearly in the
center of the image
it's fascinating it's and i didn't know
about it until 2018
when these two kids were playing in the
water
right and i said this is a new
generation saying
pay attention to it at least that's how
i see it
it's it's the next generation is saying
pay attention to the water
because we're going to need that and
that kid playing with my daughter
was martine's grandson
wow okay the connection it's good
lovely no because yeah see and again
it's it's allowing
serendipity and life through serendipity
to play it's it's meaningful role like
those two
like finding the meaning and those two
because i mean martinez
a remarkable man and what he's already
achieved
um i mean uh right livelihood award
winner for
his work on on protecting the largest
area of
amazons on rainforest um in colombia
um so but but what is it exactly that
that this project is supporting now that
the partnership between
um guayaqui and um
so it's you know we're paying
annual fees to gaia amazonas which is
the foundation
that martinez started 40 years ago and
you know um it's paying for the
leadership
program of young you know indigenous
girls and and and boys that are going to
be the stewards of this land
you know and we're talking about a huge
amount
of you know the size of france right i
mean we're
25 million hectares i mean it's it's
huge
right it's it's an area that that it was
it was all public land
until martin helped through
the colombian congress
to to make it indigenous lands and also
on top of that
but you know protect the all the natural
resources below the the soil
and and created national parks right
that are managed
and stored by the indigenous knowledge
so is it
that because that was one of my my
worries um with regard to
in so many countries you can be given
land ownership but you're not allowed
you don't have the ownership for what's
underneath the land and then
it's always the back door for the
national government to be able to
um relocate people and
disown people because they say well
we've discovered a mine underneath your
land and that's national
um jurisdiction so so martin actually
protected help to protect that as well
exactly by the developing uh you know
all these lands as
national parks and if you think about it
the amazon is a garden has been
really uh managed by the indigenous
knowledge you know of slash and burn and
moving on and the tegra beta and
it's it's really a garden you know so
recovering that knowledge and empowering
that identity
of these communities it's it's not only
a benefit for the
for them but it's a benefit for all of
us and for future generations as well
right the amazon it's a key ecosystem
that the entire planet needs
and millions of people depend on
and and businesses too and in particular
in in the south
of the amazon in in the whole um
plata uh basin rio de la plata river
plate
basin depends over 50
you know of of this rain water and um
and we're already seeing the the
the rain it's it's diminishing that the
rainfall
is going down because the amazon forest
is is being burned down so it's good
the consequences are going to be
disastrous from
many perspectives from ecosystems
economy social you know
justice um so
it it doesn't really make any sense for
us to
to burn these ecosystems on the contrary
what white
is doing is it's internalizing this
externality of the water
and really just making it you know sort
of like
hey you know we're doing it let's let's
all do it
you know because it's not only guayaquil
that's going to save the
the amazon rainforest or the atlantic
parts we all need
part of it you know it's it's giving an
example of that kind of um
[Music]
systemic reciprocity or it's even more
than reciprocity because it's
like of course you get the water but
you're supporting a process that is much
more
diffusely salutogenic health generating
in the in the region
on so many levels it's it's all those
tribes have a benefit
from owning their land and having
sovereignty
and and then you get the water as but
but also
i love the way that you brought in the
sahara because that that's
also like if you spin that cycle even
further
then so much of the fertility of the
amazon
is partially the careful management of
of the indigenous people living
living there um over over millennia but
also
um the the bigger wind patterns
that that bring um the nutrients from
the sahara
and and so even further upstream of
your plantations of of hereby
is also the the whole sahara desert
and the winds that cross the sahara
desert so
there's even a possibility to link into
the
great wall of africa project the
reforestation around the southern
um part of the sahara desert because
that also helps to
maintain the health of those circulatory
patterns
and as we as we spin around the globe
yeah
it it's it's certain
to think africa you know and you know
this
this interdependency you know it goes
daniel in so many levels you're right
because
um like like i shared you know we
started with the market driven
conservation
concept right and then we went to the
market driven restoration
and now we're talking about market
driven regeneration
and where we hold that the regeneration
we love your definition of regeneration
you know this capacity of change and
to to maintain life systems
and as as we go into into
learning more about regeneration we find
that the real regenerators
in the forest uh the flora and fauna
are the the biggest the mammals that the
trees that you know these are the
real regenerators and so so
some some you know some are calling it
rewilding and
you know bringing you know back the
species that have been extinct
and sort of like the the wolf in
yellowstone right and
that has through the cascading effect of
the trophic effect
has regenerated all the ecosystem back
in yellowstone how
you know and uh and balanced it right
and
this this is something that's being done
in in argentina through the tompkins
foundation and um now it's called rewi
in argentina
and um and they're reintroducing you
know species like the jower and the ant
eaters
to balance again you know the ecosystems
that
have now been donated as national parks
but interesting enough
when i asked uh doug tompkins before he
died
and i know chris tompkins very very well
for me they're
you know i look upon them as
as real teachers um they said well we
learned this from from
africa i said what do you what do you
mean well yeah we
you know there's there's a place called
pinda in in the north of south africa
and and dave that is that was an area
that was
you know all with with the colonialism
it was all
you know all the wildlife was gone and
there was plantations of
pineapple and you know cattle and fences
everywhere
and eucalyptus plantations and
many years ago um a group called pinda
bought that land and reintroduced the
the the wildlife
preachers the elephants the the you know
the big farm you know the largest
farmers you know in in africa reaches
the alliance
start reintroducing and develop this
business you know
that is that it's for tourism to to go
and do
watch safari and watch all this wildlife
and and i was inspired by them through
this rewinding process because
they generated through tourism you know
um
income and they also were able to work
with the zulu communities
living around these areas that were very
very poor at that time
and now they're part of their stewards
they're they're the park rangers they're
they're the ones running the the
business you know
so i went to bender
last year and then as i have to go and
visit this place
and i went there with my son who was 17
or 15 years old and i said
okay let's go to a trip let's go to
africa he was
fascinated and said well let's go and
let's go and
learn from this experience here and i
went to bender
and and i was sitting down there talking
with the park rangers
the sulu park rangers native from from
that land
and i said to them do you do you ever
have you ever heard about
tonkins listen no we have no idea
well do you know that he was inspired by
the work that you've done here
he took this inspiration the purpose
of what you've done here locally with
great success
right and reach other back all the life
yeah
well somebody else saw what you've done
here
and took it across the atlantic ocean
just like
the sun dust from the sahara took it to
the atlantic
over the atlantic to south america and
has
regenerated millions of hectares into
parks and rewire this area and bring
tourism and bring
you know community development to all
this area thanks to what you've done
here
yeah so here's the how did they
how did they respond how did they
they were surprised and they they
couldn't believe that what if
that the purpose of their work on a
daily basis on a local level has an
impact on the regional level and on the
global
see this this is this is what we all
need to understand
is that this is such a good example of
that the only like bill reid from the
genesis group
one of the the kind of
gospel holders of of truly regenerative
works so to speak
is um he
always says that and now i've not lost
my train um i am
i'm talking about place like he said to
me once
we can't heal the world we can't
save the world but we can save places
but because places are always fractal
they're always that local place that
local community that
specific ecosystem but they're also the
earth they're everything
and so the only way to get anywhere
close to healing the earth and
through that also healing her people is
to engage
people in healing place um
local place and and then the ripple
effects can be so much
higher than than you could ever imagine
because these these people
probably were proud to be part of a
project that over 30 years did that
amazing work in um south africa but
hadn't been made aware of the fact that
that also
spun off a project that is is vastly
larger
um in south america it's
it's just beautiful example of of we all
just need to do our bit
and and that then inspires others
yeah we're connected we're we you know
in every it's the butterfly effect right
it's
it it does have an impact whatever you
do you know in any part of the world
so that's why it's really important to
strengthen the identities
now because it is you know
each individual each human being is so
powerful and i know there is a certain
you know um you know negativity about
we humans you were destroying everything
and we humans are
7 billion and it's a population you know
crisis and
you know of the cause of all the
problems right
why why why
why are we the cause of all the problems
you only think that if you see that it's
because of this
feeling separate from the world we're
actually part of the world
and we for millennia have been
careful custodians more than even
stewards custodians of eco
ecosystems that that have um helped to
bring them to life and help to
increase diversity and and and we're
seed spreaders
as a species we've we've helped
plants moved into places that they
couldn't have
moved without us when we were still
migratory
and i'm convinced that we can and we
we're still demonstrating in so many
places around the world that we can have
a healing impact on ecosystems um
we were talking before we started
recording on all these wonderful
examples around the world where things
are coming back and
they're coming back because people in
that place are starting to love and care
and and um have a healing influence on
on the local ecosystem
yes and and exactly and there is a lot
of
you know resilience in in
in many communities around the planet
that
have been able to you know live
with with nature and in you know we're
talking about two million
you know what they call it like martine
the anthropologist from colombia martin
von hildebrand speaks about
you know two million indigenous
communities not too many in population i
don't know how many communities but
living in the amazon before
the spaniards arrive in the portuguese
managing this ecosystem it's not like
they were
you know just living out of of nature
they were actually
farming hunting in specific moons
in specific with and monastery
discipline it's not like okay now i feel
like eating or
a fruit and i go i just grab it no
no no but they're totally tuned
with nature and they were able to speak
with the plants
and with the stars and with the earth
and that is the knowledge that i think
you know we need to recover we
as a society you know and um
i think it was wade davis
the famous anthropologist too from from
ethnobotanist from
from bc um in in the
in the trail of the anaconda which is
the movie that they made about
martinez life and and and way dave's
life and
working with indigenous communities in
the amazon and
he he referenced it as as well
if if we are taught as
in a young age that uh mountains and
rivers are resources that we could use
to exploit um well then we we're not
going to care about doing that
but if we're taught that
these mountains and these rivers are
sacred we're not gonna just
you know mine them and contaminate them
with
you know with mercury and cyanide you
know to extract the
new gold out of it because they're
they're sacred
they're we are nature we are the rivers
this is one one of the things that when
we when we spoke with martin about
the project um a few months ago um
the way he was describing how every
ritual
every song every dance is a way of
cultural transmission from one
generation to the next to understand
um the patterns of the forest and how to
not not only interact with it in terms
of as an other but but actually
the way i heard him describe the
relationship with the forest
is really being expressions of the
forest being
like the the the the tribes are
fitting into the patterns of the larger
whole
that brought them forth and they're
they're expressing their uniqueness
by being in co-evolving mutuality or
healing support of the larger hole that
actually enables them and that that's at
the core
of of regenerative practice how do we um
express our identity and our essence of
of unique
contribution to life as life
in the wider context by serving by
giving more to the larger context
than we are taking from it and it's
actually in that process that we
express our unique gift the
in in the best way um and
that's the sort of re-indigenization
process i think we all
need to go through around the world now
of of coming home to place
as communities of i don't think this is
just that the realm of
um the remnant um indigenous
nations that are still around the world
but but it's actually
the job of all of us because all of us
are indigenous to
to planet earth you i mean the way you
speak
um the relationship you have with
with um is as you were speaking earlier
a couple of times
it reminded me of um when
when paul stomach speaks about mushrooms
um
it literally had at that sense of it's
the mushrooms talking
in the form of a human being like they
and and i i mean that as a great
compliment
um and i think that's what we all need
to
learn to speak let the
the wider whole that we are speak
through us again and and that's the big
lesson from
indigenous people that's why they
managed to live within bioregional
um boundaries in ways that that actually
generated
shared abundance for for
millennia yes
yes and
yeah yeah you know i'm i was just
thinking about um you know
a project in in peru that was
trying to clone some
towers you know and and so
in order to to make this process a
little bit you know more
um more down to earth if you want
um they they called in one one of the
indigenous
shamans from from a local tribe you know
and uh
and he said
if the jower is gonna disappear it's
because
he he wants to disappear there's no way
you're gonna
you're gonna avoid you know that
from a curing you know so the cards are
like the cards are already played and it
and it's it goes beyond what we can do
and what we can
you know and and i mean i think
the message there to me is
that if we tap into
the knowledge that nature has
you know glaciers
mountains trees that have
you know their the passing knowledge
millions of years old and we tap into
that
then it's you know we're not gonna
we're not gonna destroy ourselves you
know we're gonna
all of a sudden tap into the knowledge
the universal knowledge of life
yes and we will find our role and
function
as another species in in this
mothership that is not only
a closed
sphere but that is also influenced
by the planets and the universe and
everything
we started supporting you know we've
always supported bioneers and i know
you're
you're very close to nina siemens too
and this is one of the elements that we
also believe that
we want to support you know and um
that that there's other forces
also that we need to pay attention that
are
beyond the earth our
close sphere of life
there is other life even
outside our sphere
you know absolutely there's a real
danger of
um becoming a kind of guy in
reductionist and
and being so guy eccentric that you
don't understand how gaia sits in a
larger
um cosmic context and is it's just one
expression of probably a huge diversity
of life exploring
other journeys in other places it's just
it doesn't make any sense whatsoever to
to think of the universe as only having
life on planet earth
and actually once once we get into the
whole conversation around
what is life um and what is matter
and that whole separation of dead matter
and living bodies is is much more
um
[Music]
participatory rather than separate then
then um modern science
in the traditional sense has has made us
believe but even now modern science is
starting to understand
that um we might have got it wrong
that maybe consciousness is primary and
meta is secondary and and that really is
what also a
lot of the indigenous wisdom keepers
uh are holding this this connection to
as you were speaking
learning not just from nature but as
nature where
mountains aren't just sacred and the
rivers aren't just sacred their
ancestors they're part of our lineage
and when once we once we connect into
that lineage
we're not so speciesist anymore we're
not that
trapped in our individual or
our human identity to the point that we
that
aligning with that impulse of life that
is also
if we humans need to disappear we will
disappear um
but but that's not the end of the story
and it's not
the end of our identity because we have
a dual identity where life
and we're human human um and and
hopefully i mean you and i i think both
share the belief that that we still have
a role as human beings to
to address some of the damage that we've
done over the last few thousand years
um and to fully reach our potential of
of being
exactly what you were alluding to just
now the
the local
expression of of that capable to receive
the connection to life in other places
around the planet to even have that
that that the mental frames to explore
our beyond planet connection to to a
living cosmos
and that's that's one of the reasons why
i think that we're still worth
um for us human beings otherwise it
would be too easy to say
we're we're only making things worse
we're not
and there's so much we we can do
can you hold on just a minute
okay come back sir excellent
right um this has been a wonderful
conversation so far
we always have a have a way of finding
version
um i feel like i'm one of those elements
rockets that just went out of space and
now we're back
exactly we have i've just landed again
um
there was one thing that actually two
things that i wanted to
um mention in this conversation one of
the um
is about your work as a food scientist
when you were studying food science
like the hiroba mate as a as a plant has
a hundred and what was it 96
active ingredients um have you have you
done a lot of research
into kind of medicinal and health
properties and
and all that as well um and
and also i'm curious about the whole
what you actually bring together in the
in the product like
there's there's the the um
also all sorts of other spices and that
each one of those spice probably has
another
whole story line of connection to
community where it's produced and all
that
and and have you started to explore all
those
kind of mycelial
yes patterns of your company
yeah yeah i love how you refer
to the mycelium and concept because
you know that's i i truly believe in
that and
um i remember meeting paul stamets in
in uh in sweden 10 10 years ago i met
also um at that time john liu and
martine
you know we all met at that time back in
sweden
and one of these talber foundation
gatherings and
and it you know as we get into
you know even like zach bush talks about
you know
how each cell has maybe
between 800 and 3 thousand meteor
countries you know that
are in constant communication among each
other
with the cell and then as well each cell
with
with each organ and each body and and
[Music]
so we do the same thing as as you know
as a business as a
you know as we also look at it as a
living entity
and um i'm not only looking at the yerba
mate which is the main ingredient and
the beverages that we make but
all the ingredients that go together
with it
sugar you know working together with you
know regenerative project in
brazil of organic for trade sugar and
um paying attention they're paying
attention with
with uh the extract of yerba mate that
it's
done in in brazil and now that company
is
is becoming a v corp um so
we we're seeing you know that
an emergence of of consciousness and
or purpose all along our supply chain
and around the life cycle of the product
and um i think one of the differences
that people feel when they drink the
mate
in the can even even if it's not in the
traditional way
which you know you have all the stems
and leaves of the pen
in here with the 196 active ingredients
like you said
i actually say that 197 we're we're the
yeah right we're the other ingredient um
it's when when you
when you look at the plant at the
yavamata plant
and its environment where it grows
naturally it's in the forest
you know and it's considered a sacred
plant it's considered a mother plant
because one of those plants that has
certainly so many active ingredients
most plants have
20 40 active ingredients
there's few plants that have you know
200 or above 200
like the coca leaf or the yamamoto
marijuana
you know there is these particular
plants have so many active ingredients
because they they are a representation
of their ecosystem as well
right and the yellow mate i think
one when we produce the yellow mater
drinks we
we create an infusion we put
infusion like you would you know like
you would do it at home with
hot water and you just put all the herbs
in there
and we create an infusion and we heat it
up
and that's what we pour into our drinks
together with some of the yerba latte
extract
as well um and this
and ginger and grapefruit and
they all come from sources that fair
trade 100 of our sources are fair trade
and organic
right um and we recently
have also sort of like gone down the the
path of
well if there is a if there is a
regenerative certification
and there is a movement to do it and
well let's be part of that
rock certification so we were part of
that initial pilot
project that certified you know
regenerative
products called rock right tell me
tell me a bit more about that because i
i know that there's a new
regenerative agricultural that that has
been developed and i think you were also
somehow involved in that team
is that right we were involved together
with you know with patagonia dr
bronner's just to mention a few
but um to develop this
this certification that that goes beyond
organic right that
that is trying to to regenerate also
you know the the life back into the soil
and not just sustain it right um
but to increase it and it's not
difficult to do
it's it's something that is completely
possible
changing in our practices our you know
going back to unsavory how do we
holistic manage you know don't don't
blame the resource don't blame the cow
don't play in
fossil fuel it's that's not you know
why we have climate change here the
reason why we have it is because of how
we manage
right these life supporting systems
so rock is putting attention to that is
looking at the farm as a living system
and not as a resource
that you can farm without any
agrochemicals right but that you can
actually
regenerate that ecosystem back to
to its life with the mycociliums and
um the life below the soil
above the soil into relationships and
interdependences that
exist among not only the
crop that you're actually farming
but the crop depends of of all that
ecosystem depends on the birds
it depends on those seeds that the birds
bring and that
you know brick trees and that at the
same time are retaining the
right amount of shade and humidity
that that soil needs and that all those
microorganisms
need to sustain
and regenerate life and there's
more birds to come and there's then the
tapirs and then the jaguars that eat
that appears that also need to be there
because otherwise
the tapis would just eat everything
so it's that looking at at what you're
farming as a living entity is the key
you know and when we go back to the
yavamata we put it in a beverage
this year mate has it's grown in the
rainforest
so you're not only drinking the yellow
mate you're drinking
the yerba mate plant which is a
representation
of all that living system
[Music]
all the difference it would be really
interesting in a kind of
food science way to analyze the
difference between
um sun-grown conventional hiramate
plantations
um that i mean you you kind of invented
that the shade grown here ramada process
to
to grow commercially in the shade
because at that time most
most of the plantations were
monocultures in the sun
or yes we just paid attention to how
how was it occurring in nature we just
paid attention to nature
you know and just made up like they say
a good farmer is one that
it's it's it's a good observer
you have to observe and
are there any studies of comparing the
the kind of monocultural growth
here and its ingredients with
shade grown and how they differ
yes yes there we have a lot
different studies i mean i wouldn't say
lots of studies there's a lot more
um but we have one of carbon you know
the carbon
stock um it goes from 30
tons a hectare in a sun-grown
conventional
you know roundup run yerba mate
plantation which is the
ninety percent of how yellow markets
grown
um to 120 when it's grown in the forest
so 120 tons that's one indicator
the other one that we did measure that
was really interesting too
is um the active ingredients
the the level of each
active ingredient no um on the aromatase
shake grown cultivation is higher so
take potassium iron magnesium
just imagine through chlorophyll um
caffeine um theobromine
some of these active ingredients are
higher
in the shade grown the versus the
sunburn it makes sense right
it's the the sun grown is stressed
exactly it's a stressed plant that is
under
with lack of nutrition yeah where
the shade grown it's thriving
and it's in its environment no
so it's all the active but another
interesting one
is that when it comes down to airborne
contamination
yes why because the actual shade
protects the plant
from the yellow material from the
airborne contaminants
they come from you know from china
they cross in seven to ten days the
pacific
and they land in all our crops
in in the americas all around the world
now right
there is a lot of airborne contamination
in all of our crops
because of the pollution not only local
not in the region
but even the one that's crossing the
atlantic
even micro even micro plastics i mean if
they find micro plastics at the north
pole then the micro plastics are also
raining down on
the match atlantica for sure so we did
you know uh what's called an organic
volatile
test that measures you know hundreds of
of
of active contaminants um
um it's a very sensitive test very
briefly in
parentheses do you know that this is one
of those interesting stories
the instrument that makes that analysis
possible was invented by james lovelock
really no he invented
he he was really a a chemist and an
instrument maker um in the university in
london
when they they challenged him to to make
this thing called the
electron capture detector and it
is able to measure such minute
concentrations
in air that with without
that instrument none of the data would
have been generated
that was the basis of rachel carson's
silent spring
oh wow i mean just talking in terms of
connections
oh man
so sorry i interrupted you um you you
would you know
so we did all these you know
samples and you know with our team we
have
ethnobotanist teams and and um so
so we're looking at different patterns
and relationships
that um that would you know all these
farewells that would determine you know
what
what influences all these contaminants
or active ingredients
well when we went to the contaminants we
we clearly saw that as you would go
further into the shade grown yaro mate
plantations
there will be no contaminants as you
would
towards the sun grow higher contaminants
right yeah kind of makes sense because
they rain down on things
and if you have a lost canopy above you
it rains down on the plants above
and what happens with climate change you
know now so
now you have the the conventional
crops declining in yields
year after year obviously there is
droughts when it rains it pours with
rain and it's like like 300 millimeters
in 24 hours and
you know it just kills all the flowers
and
leaves and it's a disaster right so it's
the the actual yields of conventional
crops uh
not only of yerba mate are declining
they're going down
what happens this in the shade ground
they don't decline they stay
they stay why because they're more
resilient
there's more humidity in the soil
if it rains or hail comes it's protected
there's higher resilience there's less
there's less contaminants even even that
even even you mentioned
john elkington with violence at that
time there was also
a really good friend of mine from school
working together with him
alejandro litovsky i met him at pioneers
europe when i
when i helped kenny and nina organize
the first pioneers
conference he was one of the speakers
because he had
done the report on ecosystems economics
at the time yeah
yes and you know alejandro now
has the the um earth security
what is it called earth security network
which
analyzes the risk factors
that investments have all around the
world
due to climate change right and one of
the reports he shared with me
about coffee was
there is going to be a lack of supply
and coffee
in the years to come due to climate
change because
coffee depends on a very small window
of 10 to 15 days of flowering
yeah no that's it if that
flower doesn't get pollenized in those
you you don't have your beans you don't
have your seed you don't have your end
product
and due to climate change you know
rainfall
pouring in those days throws all the
flowers to the floor
no more crop right or changes in
temperature changes in in
community that the coffee plant needs so
there's a reduction
on the yields of coffee and one of the
things he proposed as a solution
is where does how does coffee grow
it just let's go and look at
nature there's the answers are there
it's not rocket science so much of what
we
what we harvest we could plant in
agroforestry systems together with
trees that we also selectively
regeneratively harvest for
for biomass or for for by materials for
other ingredients that aren't just
food plants um and i mean this is this
is starting to happen
in more and more places um but
is it happening fast enough i mean i one
thing that struck me when i was
looking at some of the past videos is
that the figures around
how much of the mata atlantica is
actually still left of the
of the atlantic forest um there were
different figures from five to seven
percent and i was
wondering that that made me wonder um
is it beginning to grow again or is it
still declining
the percentage that is still left
it it it is still it's sort of like
stagnant
right there because it's those remnants
are
in indigenous communities small
agricultural farmers
national parks state parks and municipal
parks that's
it yes if you look at that five percent
those are the stakeholders
that are living in this remnants
and they're holding that five percent
but
there's another issue right
if that ecosystem depends on the
rainfall produced
by the amazon and the amazon has been
cut
then this is going to all be converted
into
deforestation won't happen um
yes the plants start changing you you
start
to have more you know um
drought resistant plants that then
overtake that
that ecosystem so
the that's what carlos nobody
to is if we if we kill the amazon
there's going to be a complete change in
all ecosystems
in south america i mean that in many
ways like i was just today
um looking at the wwf's
um 2020 living planet report
and and on the one hand it shows
one striking thing which is that even
now we can already see that that we're
having less
impact because we slowed down because of
the pandemic
um same as as um i don't know if you've
saw this but seen this but the the world
overshoot day
the earth overshoot day where where
humanity as a whole has used up all
the resources that have been generated
by earth in that year
plus the capacity of the earth to absorb
it which has been moving
since 1970 from
december steadily earlier and earlier in
the year
and last year it was on the 28th of july
this year it was on the 22nd of august
it was the first year in all that time
since the 1970s that it made a 23-day
jump
um back towards uh
the positive towards reducing uh
overshoot
and it's because of the the pandemic
but what what the report on the negative
side shows is that
that species loss is
increasing everywhere
it's in different continents at
different rates and africa
is losing species even faster than
anywhere else
um but of course along with that and
along with climate change
you have a cascade of ecosystems
collapses
and changes of vegetation patterns of of
things like we use
alluding to with the coffee of the
pollinators
and the pollinated not meeting each
other anymore because
the climate zones change in local areas
even just
you know and i was talking to edward
miller and this is in
costa rica observable at different
altitudes
on the same mountain you can see how
things are changing
because the moisture doesn't come up the
mountain as far anymore because because
of climate
patterns and so on and that means that
ultimately we
more than ever we're as we're
learning to be custodians
and stewards of nature and healing
influences in the natural ecosystems we
participate in
we're so moving like working with moving
targets because they're constantly
changing and unfortunately right now
they're
um changing in the wrong direction so so
it's it's this
how do we actually decide what to plant
and how in one area
when we know that in 10 years time that
area will have a very different climate
pattern and
um so so it's the whole
temporal dimension of adaptive
agriculture and anticipatory
um regenerative agriculture to to know
what will come
in 10 years time with climate change and
anticipate
by what you planned yeah you know
i think um it's you know and
add in the fires right so
into it into the equation and you know
all of a sudden
you know you have tremendous amount of
fires and appearing as well
in close areas where we're you know have
the shade grown
near a mountain i mean the fires are
very close so you know we
we actually train we have a training
program for all our communities
to with the fire departments
and and you know making these barriers
you know to to
to sustain from the fire from
you know moving into these these last
remnants of
atlantic forests if you may right so
um i i mean
there is a lot of uncertainties right
and i think that
um we don't have all the answers and i
don't think it's one
answer either um i think
uh interesting enough even even when you
grow
in a permaculture plot crops
um you can you can imitate the forest in
those
lettuce and and and um eggplants
and bananas and you can you can create
us
the same succession the same dynamic
succession
that occurs in the forest you can
imitate in a garden
and you can create a a micro ecosystem
there right that that brings
back you know the different crops a
different timing
and producing it at different seasons
that allow for the life cycle
of life to sustain when
as he said in the beginning diversity is
the currency
and the the the here in mallorca for
example
um traditionally there were 47 or 48
different types of almond trees that
people grew around the island because
each one of them
um flowers at slightly different times
of the year and as
you said like weather is unpredictable
so sometimes if
the early flowering ones sometimes get
lucky because it's a sunny
sunny period and the bees are out
sometimes they don't get
lucky at all because the bees are still
asleep because the temperature is too
low and the and the bees come out
the week after the early flowering
almonds have basically not been
been um pollinated and it so so it is
it's the the tendency to towards
monoculture that made the
um system so brittle and if we
have more diversity like luckily we have
a few years
we have a few um kind of passionate
people that like there's one guy who's
got 200 and some
species of fig trees that he's collected
himself
from all around the mediterranean basis
a basin
and in just as one thing thinker there
there's that the highest
diversity of fig trees anywhere in the
world
and it's those kind of projects that are
actually the the
the seed banks and the the the arkanoas
of the of the future
um that it will enable us to respond
to to climate change if we if we pay
attention to that diversity
uh exactly i mean i was i was
you know that that currency
you know concept of of you know
diversity being the the
present currencies it was coined by tom
newmark
a really close friend of mine and of
course
um recently because he he was in
in luna luna nueva in his finca in costa
rica
called luna nueva that um you know he he
told the story that you know he started
doing organic farming
and then you know he realized that it
wasn't enough
and then he started you know doing
biodynamic
farming and he also noticed that
that that increased a lot but still you
know he was in
in this lineal you know plots
it wasn't until he started imitating the
forest
you know and creating of this secession
dynamic succession of crops growing
crops
not in the linear way anymore that it
it's just started thriving and that's
why he called it luna nueva like okay
i have to pay attention to to a lot of
things here
you know and and they're all here and
they're all in front of us
and i think that um the
pandemic has allowed a lot of people
to look at growing food again
reducing waste even in urban areas right
and really looking at what
environment they're they're living in
and what can they do
i am even i'm putting up a beehive
here in my house in what on site is you
know
and we started doing you know our own
detergent with the orange peels
and we started doing our own vinegar
with the apples and we started doing our
kefir drink so we don't you know we
don't have plastic
wonderful projects to do with the
children as well like it when you can do
like rather than thinking of these
projects as oh i don't have time to
play around with this make it part of
the family journey and then it's it's
really exciting
yeah and you know my son is 16 years old
and he wants to guess what he wants to
go to california and study food science
that's sweet which is great but i want
i want did i did food science
but i had to like go around the block
to to come to the to the essence of
preparing food again
how it was done you know
thousands of years ago fermented foods
and
you know not industrializing
food as a commodity and
preserving it for wartimes
in cans and it's ridiculous for us to be
buying uh tomatoes in a can
that was that was the food industry the
food science
that developed that in order to consume
it
in wartime
if if you go to a supermarket
most of the products they're filled with
with packaging and are industrialized in
in a way to
look at the expiration date the last two
years
but we actually by the yeah
yeah brilliant it's my bible for
for so
so i said i said to my son i said look
you're you can go and study food science
if you want
and and the whole industrialization of
food
but here you know you're already a food
scientist
at home he prepares the kefir together
with his brother seferino
and they do it every three days and
they're the ones in charge
of doing the kefir which is a fermented
beverage that feeds our gut
with the with the i call it the flour
and fountain it's not the flour
but with all the microorganisms that
build our immune system and that help us
from getting diseases and um
and i think that's that's the way to go
really that's you know if we all do this
uber you know farming
in our communities with the crops that
we have with the figs and mallorca
with the potatoes in chile chile that
have
280 potatoes and varieties
if you're doing the forest or in
california
we can there there is enough for man's
needs but not enough for man's great
like like gandhi
right i mean that was one of the
principles
that made me in school in food science
changed my my paradigm as well
right it was like you know it was a food
politics
course that i took taught by this
kokumo by this nigerian professor that
had malaria
he was a wonderful teacher like we
always have these teachers that change
our
our perspectives in in in college
and this this wonderful professor said
it was it was why is there hunger
in the world and there was a question
that he never answered
but gave us all the tools
just just continue asking ourselves that
question
yeah why is there food
when we have enough food to grow
everywhere and supply ourselves with now
but
there's not enough for man's greed
and that's where gandhi's coined that
statement by saying with greed
we're done that's a
that's an excellent place to finish i
unfortunately have a call in in four
minutes so i have to finish
um but before before that just wanted to
double check
are you aware of the project that
christopher nesbit is doing in release
maya mountain farms
i i should put you in touch with him and
when when travels are possible again
you would love meeting this man he's
he's um doing
regenerative agriculture in belize um is
expert on
on growing diverse ecosystems he's done
a lot of work on chocolate
with with um kind of green and blacks
when they were still a
very special company and now they've
been brought up and done i would love to
meet him yeah
and know more about it i know belize is
one of the pioneers in
in regenerating the the coral reefs as
well
yeah i mean that's that's another whole
story did tom guerrero you know
in his work on coral reefs
otherwise i had a conversation with him
a while ago
tom guerrero is this um born in the
caribbean
to both parents marine scientists
um he's an atmospheric scientist marine
scientist whatever
and and he's developed to like he worked
with a guy
who was doing this for other reasons but
then
improved the the technology basically
he's shown that if you
um put a small metal grid
into the ocean like anchored on the
ocean floor
and you replant corals in in the
in an area where there's a microcurrent
of electricity
that you put onto that metal grid
underwater then
it's that micro current that enables
the coral to take
energy from that that is used to
for the basic physiological processes of
keeping the coral in the moment
but that energy then is freed up for the
coral to grow quicker
so he's demonstrated that by using this
very
low invasive technique of just putting
this metal grid which
eventually dissolves in the ocean
um you can regrow coral
at four or five times the rate and more
then they naturally
re regenerate and it and he's recently
done more studies on sea grass matters
which are also
carbon sequesters from from the ocean
and it's
like critically important for ocean
health and and you can also regrow
sea grass much faster when you do this
i'll send you the link it's fascinating
work
but unfortunately i have to um
finish because
okay um daniel yeah i have a one o'clock
meeting too i just want to say one more
thing i'm going to send you i don't know
if i send it to you but
you know we we did an internal just
workshop um with with um it started it
it started off with with the earth
charter um
you know on on an earth day and what
they set up there with with free
opera and samuel um and um
i think it was it was money nasiru
there was a couple of speakers that were
wonderful and talking about the pandemic
and everything and we started off with
all of the team in guayaquil in south
america
um watching that and then each one just
sort of like pointing out
you know what what was you know
identified by
each individual of these great speakers
that we're sharing and
but anyway from there just went into
your
your book and we we applied
sort of your principle of you know of
the
of the symbol of infinite symbol with
the four
elements yeah with with the
with the that curve that life cycle
curve of where you know we're faced with
death
and rebirth and reorganization
and regrowth and we we used
we have used that as our principle
now in guayaquil in in south america
to recognize and even in north america
to
to recognize that we need to allow this
cycle
this dynamic cycle to flow
so i just want to know that i have a
presentation that it's documented
very nicely and in english that i would
love to share with you because
it is something that you can also share
of how your theories and your
experience in your book and everything
is being applied also in the in
in the business wow thanks for that i
mean it's it's not my
the adaptive cycle is kind of distilled
wisdom of 40 years of the people and the
resilience alliance which are ecosystems
resilience people buzz hauling and those
kind of gunderson and so on
those ecosystem scientists looking at
change patterns and evolution patterns
in
ecosystems and what what basically how
ecosystems function
and and that's what when they distilled
that they they came to
the adaptive cycle and the monarchy that
these adaptive cycles are nested
through spatial temporal scale linking
and and so basically it just perfectly
fits
for a company that that is aligned with
natural patterns
and driven as nature for nature to to
align with those patterns really
exciting it was perfect it was it was
fantastic it was wonderful so thank you
and let's catch up again soon on off
recording
already